fact zoom. Tell me how many people have
zoom.
So, do we have people in Zoom? How many?
The class is getting awfully sparse.
You know what? I think I want to
upweight the second half of the semester
for attendance and downweight the first
half.
Upweight the second half of the semester
for attendance.
exponentially, you know, increasing
weight.
>> 10% of your points attendance.
>> How does it sound, guys? I uh
changed my scoring policy. 10% of your
marks are for attendance and I upgrade
the second half of the semester. So, you
know, as the classes pass, each class
card is worth twice as many points as
the previous one,
right?
>> That would work, right?
>> Okay. I think can we take a vote on
that?
Raise your arms if you're if you're okay
with the policy.
Okay, guys. You are in class. This has
been noted. I have taken a vote and so
we've all decided collectively
that uh 10% of the marks for this class
are going to come from attendance
and furthermore that the uh attendance
waiting policy is going to have an
increasing weight as the semester passes
which means this week is worth twice as
many points as the last week which is
worth twice as many points as the
previous week. So this is to be noted. I
have a vote. It has been passed.
>> Okay.
>> FC about to get approved.
>> That's okay. Public opinion. Come on.
Right.
So, let's start. Uh,
we're going to be talking about
generative adversarial networks today.
I'll be doing the lecture along with
Ming Jang. She's our TA. Historically,
this lecture has been uh split between
me and a teaching assistant. Mia's done
it. Mas has done it. you know this time
it's uh me mention the slides that we'll
be using today are in part by how Chen
in the second half and the first in the
first half many of the slides are by Ben
Shriner who was a TA back in 2018
so
we've learned about VAES we've learned
about diffusion models we're going to
learn about generative adversarial
networks we'll try to connect some dots
to recap what uh Masa mentioned in her
class
our neural network models statistical
models in general can be of two kinds.
They can be discriminative or they can
be generative. In the case of
discriminative models, you're computing
the posterior probability. So you know
here's a picture. What is the
probability that this is a picture of a
cat? What is the probability that this
is a picture of a dog? So you compute
the posterior probabilities of the
predicted variable given the input. So
uh this is generally used for performing
classification, regression and similar
tasks where the focus is on the
predicted variable. Generative models on
the other hand are about learning the
distribution of the data itself. So what
is the distribution of all pictures of
cats? What is the distribution of all
pictures of dogs? Now if you have a good
model for this uh for the distribution
of the data you can always perform
discrimination based on it but if you
can per the reverse is not necessarily
true. So this is the uh because it's
much more informative learning
generative models is a much harder
problem requiring deeper understanding
of the distribution of the data.
Now there's another uh
way of categorizing models,
generative models in particular. One is
explicit models where you actually get a
formula for the distribution of the
data. So now once you have a formula for
P of X, you can say okay here's a
picture what is the probability that
this is this you know of this picture
having come from the distribution of
cats. So you can actually compute P of X
at every X.
In the case of implicit distributions,
you have no idea what the formula is.
You don't know what the distribution
looks like yet you can sample from it.
And so uh VAE try to
obtain explicit models. But in the case
of GANs, it's going to be uh an implicit
distribution model. So here's your first
spot.
Okay, this was an easy one. What What
are the responses?
What's the answer to the first question,
guys?
On Zoom, can somebody on Zoom tell me
the answer to the first question?
Do we have a response? Is there anybody
on Zoom?
>> It's one first option.
>> First option. Okay, guys. On Zoom, you
were also part of the vote, right? If
you did not vote, well, you just didn't
vote. So, you got a chance to say yes or
no for our decision on how we're going
to be waiting attendance.
And uh your votes have been counted
because you were there. Now, what's the
answer for the second question?
Anyone here?
Hm.
>> A that's a right. So discriminative
models model the decision boundary
between classes. Generative models model
class distributions.
Explicit model compute the probability
of samples. Whereas implicit models only
let you uh allow you to sample from
these distributions. And GANs are
what are GANs? Implicit or ex implicit
or explicit guys?
Mhm.
So, do you mind shutting your laptop?
>> Oh, I'm trying to pull up the slide.
>> Okay. So, what are GANs again? Implicit
or explicit?
>> Wake up, guys. Somebody tell me. Mhm.
>> Okay. Speak up, please. Hello. Thank
you. Right. So, again, just to recap,
the problem was this. You're given a
collection of data. And from this
collection of data, you're going to have
to learn the learn how to generate more
data of similar to the class that the
data belong to. So maybe you see a
collection of pictures of faces, you
need to know how to learn to draw a
face. And we've seen one model for this
VAE.
The idea behind VAEEs was that the
distribution of any restricted category
of data, anything that's not noise is
going to lie in the restricted region of
the space which we and so we can't
characterize it. But what we can do is
to start start off with a standard
distribution like a Gaussian and then
warp it using a function that can be
learned so that it looks like the
distribution that we're interested in.
And of course so this so so this
generator is the decoder of a VAE. Now
it's not perfect. So you have to account
for the error which we are accounted by
through a noise term. And so here was
the entire uh VAE model.
You have a standard distribution that I
you start off with typically a Gaussian.
You draw samples from it. You pass it
through your function and it generates
data from the class that you're
interested in because uh this cannot be
perfect when you're actually training
the model. Uh this construction cannot
may not be perfect. You have to account
for the errors through through a noise
term. The way you this is actually an
explicit kind of model because you're
actually learning to compute the
probability of data. And so we train
this model by trying to maximize the
probability of our training data, the
likelihood of our training data. Then we
perform maximum likelihood training or
just flipping signs around you minimize
the negative log likelihood.
And this
uh gives us a model for the
distribution. But then the issue over
here is that the likelihood of your
training data doesn't really have
anything to do with whether what the
model generates looks like a face or
not. You're just looking at statistical
principles. Right? Now on the other
hand, what do I want to do? I want to
construct a model
whose
uh which
draws pictures of faces. Anytime I
sample from it, it draws a picture of a
face. What is the best laws
to train such a model? Keeping in mind
that you want the output to look like a
face. Every time you you pass a random
number through a random vector through
it, the output must look like a face. So
if
you were to be doing this, suppose you
were training a child and you ask the
child to draw a face and it draws a
blob, right? what is the feedback you're
going to give it at the highest level
right like what kind of feedback would
you give it so you know I'm trying to
draw faces and I'm pretending to learn
to draw faces and I start off with
generating say huh you know what here's
my face
what's your response
>> mhm
>> speak It's not a face.
>> It's not a face, right? Okay, fine then.
Huh? It's not a face. How about this?
>> It's not a face. What is the feedback
you've given me?
>> Does this look like a face? Right.
That's how you would actually be
training you because you want the model
specifically to be generating faces. You
want to be wanted to be
saying does this look like a face? So
that makes sense to you, right? Can we
computationalize this? How can you
comput computationalize this little
thing that you just explained to me
saying that the best way to train such a
model that what you would do is to
literally ask the question inform the
model whether this looks like a face or
not. How would you do it?
I think the first thing that I can think
of is we have a data set and we kind of
have a model that learns how a face
looks but you know we're doing the
compilational
uh that our homework we're basically
training the model like this is looks
like a face and this doesn't but then we
don't want the model to learn too much
like but what is the different is okay
so here's a poll for you right
answer the poll and yeah you're right
we'll get on
Okay, without spending too much time on
this first statement, true or false?
False.
>> Okay, second one.
What do you guys think? Would likelihood
maximization not result in a model that
produces more facelike outputs?
Right?
Why would it not produce it?
Anyone?
>> The first one.
>> Mhm.
>> The first one. The model can maximize
the likelihood of the training data
without any assurance about what the
other samples look like. Right. And so
what about the third question?
What do you guys think?
>> H true, right? So, uh, we are actually
explicit models, right? And the model
can maximize the likelihood of training
data without any assurance about what
the other
samples look like. So, it could generate
faces, it also it could also generate
garbage, right?
So what we really need is something a
loss function that explicitly tells you
whether the output is looks like a face
or not. So this is what I'm calling my
daf loss. Does this look like a face?
Does it look like a face? What's a good
daf loss over here?
Now you answered it. What's your name?
You need a name tag.
>> Mhm.
>> Juan. So Juan just gave us the answer.
uh and the basis of what a good deaf
loss is goes back to the definition of
our model itself. What is a generative
adversarial network? GANs generative
adversarial networks three components.
The first is a generative model which is
capable of generating data of the class
that you're trying to generate data from
uh like a VAE right but then you have an
adversary which actually evaluates the
output of this model. This is your dilap
loss. It says does this look like a face
and of course the whole thing is a
network neural network. So these are
GANs right uh they were originally
introduced in 2014. The goal is to model
a distribution P of X of the of the
training data. Basically want to learn a
model that can generate samples that
look like our training data. And we you
train it using a pair of models. One is
the actual generator
which generates the the samples and then
you have an adversary a discriminator
which evaluates it to tell you to inform
us whether the generator is doing the
right the right job or not. So this is
our adversaries now in fact a computed
loss. Okay.
So here's the overall structure. The
generator looks like the uh the decoder
of a variational autoenccoder. You you
pass in some noise typically a Gaussian
noise and it modifies it and generates
an output. So if I'm trying to generate
draw faces that generator should be
drawing every time you pass a sample
through it the output should look like a
face. Now the discriminator looks at the
output of this model and and decides is
does this really look like a face or
not. So the discriminator is able to
discriminate between two categories of
uh data. The first is
what the model generates and real data.
And if the discriminator does a good
job, if it's really good at
distinguishing what is fake versus what
is not fake, and if your generator can
fool this discriminator,
then whatever your generator generates
looks like the class that you're trying
to generate, right?
So what are these two guys? First is the
generator itself. The generator is
supposed to produce realistic looking
data from images X by transforming a
sample Z from your latent distribution
the initial distribution which could be
a Gaussian. And so the goal over here
I'm going to represent this as PG of X.
This PG
of X is to indicate that these are data
generated by the generator. The random
variable here is not really X. So if you
really want to think about this, you
want to think of this P of G of Z
because you're drawing Z from a Gaussian
distribution and passing it through the
generator. But for convenience sake, I'm
just going to call this PG of X just to
make it explicit that we're really
speaking of the generator. But you have
to keep in mind that the random variable
here is the Z that is going into the
generator, right?
And then the discriminator
takes in any or any any input X and its
job is to tell the difference between
real and generated that is fake data
specifically data produced by the
generator. If a perfect discriminator is
fooled then the generated data cannot be
distinguished from real data. So uh both
of these have to be trained. I cannot
just train a discriminator beforehand
saying you know this is a perfect
discriminator. It's able to distinguish
everything that's faces from everything
that's not a face and then plug it in.
If you do that, it will not work. The
discriminator has to be trained in
tandem with the generators
because you want it specifically to be
able to distinguish between what the
generator is currently generating and
what is a real instance of the class.
>> This reminds me a little bit of
diffusion that we saw last class when we
have the you know we inject noise and
then we learn the noise. in this case
how it it differentiates between
generator and discriminator because in
diffusion model we learn how to like the
noise looks like right to then take the
noise out of an image
>> we're we're not trying to extract this
is literally just transforming the
sample right so uh you're not trying the
diffusion model could be the generator
we are not really making any claim about
what the nature of the generator is
>> in the case what we are changing is the
loss that is used to train the
generator,
>> right? And the gener and the loss is the
discriminator. That's the key piece. The
GAN is modifying the loss to make it
something more natural like, you know,
is this a face?
>> So
when you're training the discriminator,
the discriminator will be provided
training examples of the actual class,
the category of data you're trying to
generate like pictures of faces and the
category of synthetic data, whatever the
generator might be generating. and it's
trained to minimize to to
maximally or distinguish between the
two. So if I if I'm thinking of a
discriminator which is whose output is a
sigmoid for instance the output goes
from 0 to one. Right? Ideally you want
the output of the discriminator to be
one
whenever it sees a real phase and you
want it to be zero when it sees a
synthetic phase that's come from the
generator. That's how the discriminator
is able to distinguish between the two.
So alternately I I can say I want the d
of x to be one for real faces and 1
minus d of x to be one for fake faces. I
can put a log on it and say I want log
of d of x to be as large as possible for
real faces and log of 1 minus d of x to
be as large as possible for synthetic
faces. And so the discriminator must be
trained to do this. It must maximize the
parameters of the discriminator must be
trained such that log of d of x is
maximized for real faces and log of 1
minus d of x is maximized for uh data
produced by the generator. Make sense to
everybody? Right? Any questions on zoom?
Okay.
What about the generator?
Now the discriminator and generator are
coupled. So the the gradients can be
passed all the way from the
discriminator to the generator. What
does the generator's job? The generator
wants to fool the discriminator. Now
remember the discriminator is trying to
output a zero anytime it sees synthetic
data. So what must the generator try to
do?
If the discriminator discriminator
outputs a zero or tries to output a zero
when it sees synthetic data and the
generator is trying to fool the
discriminator, what will it try to do?
>> So in terms of the discriminator's
output score, what does it what would it
try to do?
>> Again, keep in mind that the
discriminator outputs a one when it sees
real faces. It outputs a zero when it
sees synthetic faces. Right? What does
the generator want the discriminator to
produce? Output one
>> a one. Right? So the generator is going
to try to the generator's parameters are
trained such that this guy the
discriminator when it operates on the
generator its output goes to one because
it's trying to fool the generator. Or
alternately you want 1 minus d of g of z
to be zero. This makes sense to
everybody right?
or you know I'm trying to make 1 minus d
of g d of g of z to zero.
I'm trying to minimize 1 - d of g of z
or minimize log of 1 - 3 of g of z. So
we we keep in keep speaking in terms of
logs you don't have to the basic
principle holds how you actually compose
these losses is a bit up to us but we
will use loss the logs because uh it
gives us some nice intuition down down
the line. Okay, so here's the GAN
formulation. The discriminator for real
data, it's trying to maximize log of D
because it's trying to make the output
one. For synthetic data, it's trying to
trying to maximize log of 1 minus D
because it's trying to push D towards
zero. The generator is trying to
minimize log of 1 minus D because it's
trying to make D go towards one. Right?
If I put all of those into one single
loss. So the discriminator over all real
data. So the expectation over real data
uh you're looking at the log of d ofx
right. And so you're trying to maximize
log of d of x over real data. The
discriminator is trying to maximize log
of 1 minus d on synthetic data. So the
discriminator is always trying to
maximize this guy. it's trying right and
the generator on the other hand
this doesn't have any generator
component to it this is real data but
the generator is trying to minimize this
guy so I can put all of those into one
single loss which is log of d of x
averaged over all training samples plus
log of 1 minus d of
the output of the generator
uh again averaged over all generated
samples
This the discriminator tries to maximize
this and the generator tries to minimize
this right. So uh again objective of the
discriminator d of x must be one for
synthetic data a real data d of g of z
that's synthetic data it must be zero
objective of the generator d of g of z
must go to one right so that making
sense to everybody
right once you train this model keep in
mind that the discriminator is only the
law is is is basically a loss right it's
a daf loss does this look like a face
loss once you've trained the model you
don't keep the loss around you can throw
it away. So you can throw the
discriminator away and then what remains
is what is all that you're interested
in. So when you train it, you'd start
off first you need a loss. You always
need a loss, right? So you'd start off
by training the discriminator
using lots of you'd initialize your
generator. You have lots of real data.
The generator is going to generate some
synthetic data. You use those to update
train your loss function, your
discriminator. Then you use the last
function, the discriminator, to update
the generator. But then once you updated
it, the generator is producing something
different from what the discriminator
was trained on. So you go back and train
the discriminator and you keep repeating
this process.
Yeah, there's a problem.
It's an easy poll, guys. What's the
answer to the first question?
>> The discriminator.
>> Can you say that aloud?
>> Why?
>> Because it's the loss.
>> It's the loss. You want to train the
loss first. You always want to train the
discriminator first. Okay. What is the
answer to the second question?
>> Generator.
>> Discriminator.
>> The discriminator. Why?
>> Because if it's the loss and we're
currently trying to update it to
minimize student AB,
>> the discriminator is the loss. You want
the loss to be good. Using a crappy loss
to train your model is not a very good
idea, right? So you always focus on the
discriminator. It's the DF loss.
training the loss is more important
because the loss guides the training. So
you so do you mind shutting the laptop
back there? Okay, shut your laptop.
Yeah, sorry. Thank you. So you you start
off by training the discriminator, then
you update the generator, then you go
back and train the discriminator again.
So typically when you train these
models, you have five update steps of
the discriminator for every update step
of the generator.
So how does this whole thing behave when
each component is optimized? For this we
have to go back and look at base
classification.
Now let's say I have two classes of
data. My green are real data. Say real
data. My white are going to be synthetic
data. Right? So
my
real data has some distribution. My
synthetic data has some distribution.
Right? If I look at any location X over
here
then let's say I have a 100 let's say
this height is say.1
and let's say this height
is say
0.4 four, right? Then if I generate 100
samples of real of real data and 100
samples of synthetic data, how many of
the real data samples will have
value X
in this case? The green is real, right?
So this is the probability distribution.
This is P of X versus X. So if I
generated a 100 samples of this guy, how
many of them would have how many of the
real ones would have value X?
Exactly.
>> Speak up, please.
Come on, guys.
>> So this is going to be just 04 is a pro
is is the probability of X, right? So
you'd say 04 * if I had generated 100
samples time 100 that's how many of the
real samples are going to have
x you know that particular value of x if
I generated 100 samples of synthetic
data right how many of them would have
the x that that x value
>> 10 right 10 so this is going to be 40
this is going to be 10 so if I look at
an x value
what fraction of of them are real.
If I observe an x value, right? What at
x? What fraction of
>> 80%
>> 80%. Right? So that's the formula,
right? If you look at it, you're going
to say
this is p of x comma y is the num the
number of instances of class y that have
the value x. The den denominator is the
total number of instances of class y. So
the posterior probability of a specific
class Y as you just saw is going to be
the ratio of the number of instances of
class Y with that particular value of X
divided by all
all instances with that value of X right
the count. Yeah.
>> And how do we know the overlap
distribution?
>> We don't this so we don't this is just a
formula right and so we're just saying
this is what the posterior probability
is going to be. Now when we were talking
about classifiers
what what did we say way back when what
did we want the classifier's output to
be did we want the classifier to
deterministically say this is a face
even though you know at that value of x
you could have
non-face images right synthetic images
or did you want it to output a
probability
>> you wanted to output a probability right
and so this is the posteriority
probability you want the posterior
probability of the class given the data
at every value of x. This is what an
optimal classifier would do. It's g this
is the most informative classifier.
Right? And so
this guy is going to say what is the
probability that these data are real
for every value of x. And so
where is the perfect decision boundary?
At what value of x? If I had to choose
and assign a class at what uh you know
where do I stop saying this is synthetic
and start saying when this is real
that's going to be when the probability
of the two probabilities of both classes
are exactly the same right and once you
go to one side one class becomes more
dominant on the other side the other
class becomes more dominant so where the
two distributions cross over that's
where your decision boundary is going to
lie right make sense to everybody Okay.
So yeah,
>> how do we deal with the beginning with
cold start like if the discriminator
doesn't have enough data to determine
whether or not
>> M will talk about those things. Okay. So
we're just speaking about the
principles. So now what if I'm trying to
create a generator
who's generating
whose out output distribution is the
same as the real data,
right? What is the target distribution
for my generator over here?
What is the target distribution for my
generator?
>> The green one.
>> The green one. You want the generator's
output to be look like the green. Right?
So if this is what the generator is
generating, what do you want to do with
it?
>> I want to shift it. Right? Okay. So
here's what happens. The optimal
discriminator, this is the optimal
discriminator. It's giving you the
probabilities, right? But it's also
finding out exactly where the two the
two classes cross over and it's marks
the decision boundary. So suppose I've
optimized my discriminator.
Then I update my generator. What do I
want the generator to do?
Right.
It can yeah
>> shift.
>> I want the generator to modify the
outputs so that they get
shifted.
into the real space, right? But then if
the generator has managed to shift
things a bit, what must the
discriminator do?
>> It must learn the new boundary, right?
And so the initially the discriminator
learns the perfect boundary. The
generator moves it past the boundary
into the real one. But then you go back
and update the discriminator. It learns
the new boundary. Right? Then what will
the generator do?
discriminator.
>> So it's going to shift it again, right?
And then what will the discriminator do?
>> Learn the boundary. Then where will it
stop?
>> Did you mention that the discriminator
updates more frequently generator? But
from this picture, it seems like both.
>> No, the discriminator. It's an iterative
process. You're not going to So if I run
iterations,
you want to get the boundary. It's more
important to get the boundary. You know,
the generator doesn't have to push it
all the way in. If the generator pushes
it a little bit in, that's fine. But the
discriminator always has to find the
boundary. So, we run more iterations of
the discriminator to make sure it finds
the boundary, right? And so, where will
the whole thing stop? The whole thing is
going to stop
when they're perfectly overlapped. The
picture is making sense to everybody,
right? And so, that's why this whole
process is going to actually end up with
a generator that mimics the the
distribution of the real data.
And at that point the optimal classifier
is going to be the disc discriminator is
going to just give you the posterior
probability of real data which is px of
x. What is the probability that
this sample could have been generated
from the real distribution divided by px
of x plus pg of x. This is what the
optimal discriminator is always going to
be doing except when the things are
perfect the two two distributions in the
denominator are both going to be the
same. So this is going to be 0.5 always
right that's when the discriminator is
confused.
So let's look at what happens. Let's say
at each point I actually optimize the
discriminator. If I optimize the
discriminator then here again is the
loss. The optimal discriminator is going
to give you px divided by px plus pg. px
is the probability of computed using the
real distribution. The denominator is
you know the sum of the real and
generated distributions. Right? So let
me plug that in. Right? So this is going
to be the loss is log of d of x.
That's our discriminator plus the
expectation over all generated samples
of log of 1 minus d of x. But the d of x
of course is just px / px plus pg right
in both cases. This guy is the log of
the ratio of two terms plus the log of
the ratio of two terms. Now what exactly
is this crazy term over here? For that
let's go back and look at uh look at
divergences which compare distributions.
We are familiar with one particular
divergence cullback label divergence
right the cullback label divergence
between two distributions was defined in
this manner as the sum over all possible
values of the data of P of X * log of P
of X divided by Q of X if I'm comparing
Q P and Q or alternately I can write
this as Q * log of Q / P both are fine
right but what is the problem over here
if the term in the denominator inside
the log goes to zero this thing becomes
infinity regardless of what happens
elsewhere right so which means is that
that let's say I have two distributions
P and Q and they're perfect everywhere
but at one point just one point the
second distribution assigns a
probability of zero to a value that the
first distribution thinks has a nonzero
probability so one distribution could
say this one has a probability of 0 0 0
0 0 0 0 0 1 really smart, right? The
other guy says, "Oh, it's zero." Would
you call that bad?
This guy's going to die because there's
a division by 0, right? So, it's not a
good metric.
How can I fix this for this? Also, you
know, P of KL of PQ is not the same as
KL of QP, but the bigger issue is that
the denominator can go to zero in a
perfectly reasonable way. and yet the
whole thing can blow up on your face.
Right? So, uh the alternative is
something called the Jensen Shannon
divergence where instead of just looking
at the distributions comparing P and Q,
I'm going to compare P with the average
of P and Q, but also compare Q to the
average of P and Q. So now in this case
you can see this is.5 * the KL of P
and.5 P + Q plus.5 * the KL of Q
and the average of P and Q. And you can
see over here that the you know if
either P or Q go to zero it doesn't
really matter because the average is not
going to be zero. The only time you get
a zero in the denominator is if both P
and Q become zero. But if both p and q
become zero then uh you know this term
will also become zero right and as a
result 0 * log of 0 is zero. So that's
not a problem.
So the Jensen Shannon divergence is
symmetric and has the nice property that
it doesn't blow up. Okay. And so if you
go back and look at this formula over
here, it turns out that this formula
over here, the loss, if you've trained
your discriminator to be optimal,
the loss that you're minimizing to train
the generator is actually just the
Jensen Shannon divergence between the
out the distribution computed by the
generator and the distribution of real
data. So if you optimize your
discriminator at each step, this
training is actually minimizing the
Jensen Shannon divergence between the
real and synthetic data. So the overall
training process is you train your
discriminator, you optimize it, then you
work on the generator and the generator
minimizes the uh GS divergence between
the synthetic and real data. But then so
then you've shifted the distribution
then you go back and train your
discriminator again at each step it's
minimizing the GS divergence that make
sense to everybody right
so the optimal generator minimizes the
GS divergence between the distributions
of the actual and synthetic data and
then finally so when the whole thing
works the generator of the fully
optimized GAN is going to be where P of
G equals P of X so the discriminator
even though it's an optimal
discriminator is only going to give you
a probability of 0.5
at every x. Okay.
So at any x pg of x= px of x. So the
discriminator is going to have zero
which means the derivative it's zero
everywhere. So it has a derivative of
zero. Right?
And so how do we know this whole thing
has worked? When the derivative of the
loss of the discriminator has gone to
zero. Right? there's nothing to back
pass back propagate and so all the uh
training stops
but then so and this is the minmax
stationary point there exists a
stationary point if the generated data
exactly matches real data the
discriminator outputs 0.5 for everything
there are no there are there are no
derivatives to back propagate so the
training stops but then we have a
problem that a perfectly random
discriminator
which always generates 0.5 right that
also has a derivative of zero.
So you can see that this training is
unstable right because in that case
again there are no more derivatives to
back propagate neither the discriminator
nor the generator are going to get
updated.
So these stationary points that we get
they can they need not be stable the
generator may overshoot a discriminator
discriminator can get to be very steep
and be very confident about the wrong
answers in which case there are no
derivatives. Mangin will mention these
briefly we have a bunch of issues right.
So again the generator and the
discriminator need to be trained
simultaneously because the discriminator
must always optimize for the generator
as we just saw not just it should not be
doing a generic job of saying is this a
face or not a face it has to be
optimized for the discriminator because
that's how the the generator can shift
its distribution past the boundary.
Okay,
so the discriminator is uh undertrained,
it's random, there's going to be no
derivative. If it's overtrained, it's to
act confident, there is going to be no
derivative. Mang Mangchin will mention
these briefly. So here's the overall
process. Step one, train the
discriminator using the current
generator. Then train the generator to
beat the discriminator. Repeat the
process till the whole thing has
stopped. Uh GANs can produce really
crisp results for many problems. there
are stability issues and are hard to
train things like mode collapse
producing outputs with very low
probability and so on. Uh here's the
final poll before I hand over to nature.
Give me 2 minutes. Okay.
>> The same concept app
for instance frequencies in music for
people like applications in guns not
only holds in images but also
>> this is generated for any any data I'm
using images as examples. So what are
the answers guys?
>> Anybody want to give me the answers
here?
Someone on Zoom.
>> Option one.
>> Option one. Is option one true?
Right. So what happens if the generator
always generates a perfect face but it
only generates the same face each time?
Will it fool the discriminator?
It will. Right? But is that what you
want?
Okay. So that's one. Right. uh the
Jensen Shannon divergence may have poor
derivatives preventing the model from
training. Can that happen?
It can. Right? We'll see how. Right? The
discriminator may be random. Can that
happen? Right? We just saw that's an
issue. Right? The discriminator may be
too certain. That can also happen. We'll
see how this happens. Right? So, what
happened over here? Why did my
Did you do something?
Oh my.
Uh-oh.
Okay.
>> No, no, don't touch it. Just use the
clicker. Okay.
>> Okay.
>> All right. So
uh some general notion of
okay guys mention take over I have a I
have a tax issue
>> one second the mic mention take the mic
just skips directly to your
>> thank you everybody
Yes. Hi, I'm sorry.
>> Okay. Hello everyone. My name is Mun.
I'll continue from here and talk about
two key problems of vanilla GANs along
with a few techniques to address them.
Then I'll briefly introduce different
types of GAN architectures and some
applications.
So there are two main issues with Vina
Gans. The first one is Vination
ingredients and the second one is mode
class.
Let's start with the first one v one
gradient. So this means the generator
receive almost no useful a gradient for
learning because the discriminator does
not provide meaningful feedback. There
are a few different situations that can
all lead to this same problem.
So let's see the first situation is
related to this uh discriminator. If the
discriminator become too good it can
easily distinguish real data from
generated data. So when this happens it
outputs becomes very confident very
close to zero or one and as a result it
no longer provides useful learning
signals. So the generator cannot really
learn anything.
So let's see uh this in the right
figure.
Let me try to
can you see the Okay. So the blue
distribution is the real data and the
gray green curve shows the gen uh the
generated data and the red curve is a
discriminator.
So we can see that this discriminator
sharply separates this real data and
generated data. So that means it all
output like close to zero or close to
one.
However, if we look at this region where
this generated data lines, the red curve
is almost flat. So this means the
gradient is very small. So even though
the discriminator is cracked, it does
not pass useful gradient
to the generator.
Okay. And on the other hand, if the
discriminator is not good enough when we
sometimes call losy discriminator, then
it can can it cannot clearly tell real
and fake apart and the feedback it gives
is not reliable. So in both cases the
generator does not receive meaningful
gradients.
Okay. And also we can see this in the
figure.
So if the discriminator is very weak,
you can see from here this is a
discriminator. It's a weak
discriminator. So its outputs are almost
the same value everywhere. It's almost
0.5 everywhere regardless of whether the
sample is real or fake. So as a result,
the generator receives no useful signal
to improve.
Okay, here is a quick summary of the
discriminator issue. This
solid blue and blue uh curve represents
a strong discriminator. So you can see
this almost uh output one or zero is so
confident but this dash and orange curve
represents a weak discriminator. So you
can see it uh output around 0.55
everywhere.
So again this means it cannot
distinguish real from fake samples. So
its outputs barely change across the
inputs.
Okay. Then we come to the second
situation. Uh this is to related to the
loss function. So in vanilla games when
the real data distribution and the
generated distribution are far apart or
disjoint the discriminator can easily
separate them since the discriminator
uses a sig mode as a last layer to
produce a probability when the output is
close to zero or one the sig mode is in
a saturated region. So in this case when
the slope is almost zero uh and the
gradient is also very small.
So let's look at this. Okay, can try.
Okay, let's also look at this in the
figure for better understanding. So we
can see when the
when the real data distribution and the
generated data data distribution are far
apart from each other, the discriminator
can become very confident. It can always
separate uh real data from generated
data and it produce very large or small
values that push the sigmoid output
close to zero or one. This is zero or
one and we can see that the generated
data lies in this region. This region
the sigmo output is almost zero. So the
gradient is also near the zero and the
generator is cannot learn anything.
Okay.
Now this also leads to the next issue
the divergence problem. So to see this
more clearly let's look at a simple
example. So suppose the real data always
output zero at here and the generated
data always outputs some value theta.
uh our our goal is to get uh to push
this theta to a zero from here to here.
And so in this case the real data
distribution is a point mass at zero
here and the generated data distribution
is a point mass as data. Now the
question is how do we measure the
difference between these two
distribution.
So a natural idea is that we can try to
use cal divergence. But what happens
here?
Okay. So for the real data the
probability is one at zero and zero zero
elsewhere. for the generated data it's
one at x= to theta and zero elsewhere.
So when theta is not zero there's a
location where the real distribution is
one but the generated distribution is
zero. Then in the K formula we get a
term log of one / zero which get into
the infinity and the another term this
because it's multiply by zero so it
disappears
and also if the theta equals to zero uh
the two distribution match exactly and
the K divergence is zero.
Okay, so to sum up this is exactly what
this small plot on the right shows. The
value is zero at theta equals to zero
but jump to infinity
everywhere else. So the key problem is
not just the value is large but the but
that the objective is not differentiable
with respect to theta. So the function
is infinity almost everywhere and only
define a single point. So there is no
use for gradient to guide optimization.
So KL divergence does not work here.
Now let's try JS divergence which we
have learned before. So recall that JS
divergence is defined using an average
distribution. We define a new
distribution M which is the average of
the real and generated uh distribution.
So in this example at x= to zero the
real distribution is one and x uh equal
to and the generated distribution is
zero. So the average is 0.5
and at x= to theta it is the o o o o o o
o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o
o o o o o o o o o o o o o o opposite
offsite the real distribution is zero
and the generated distribution one. So
again this get 0.5 and so M puts
probability 0.5 at both locations. Now
we compute JS divergence which is this
two uh K term.
So uh this is one from real to M and one
from generate to M. Uh let's look at the
first one. At x= to zero the row
distribution is one and m is 0.5. So we
get a term log of one over 0.5
and which is log two and at equals to
theta the real distribution is zero. So
that this term disappears here.
So the whole first term get log two
and now the second one is symmetric. So
again we the second k term is also log
two. So log two plus log two multiply by
this 0.5 we get the total J divergence
as log two. Now there's a key point as
long as the theta is not zero the
calculation does not change. So m is
always 0.5 at both locations and both
cal terms are always log two. So the GS
divergence is always log two as we
calculate as before and no matter how
far theta is from zero
and also only when theta equals to zero
the two distributions become identical
in that case the real and generated
distributionions are exactly the same.
So m is also the same distribution and
both k terms becomes zero. So JS
divergence becomes zero and during
training as long as the distributions do
not overlap the loss stays constant and
provides no use for direction for
learning.
So similar to KL divergence uh this
objective is also not differentiable
with respect to theta. So it provides no
use for gradient. And also just a
reminder that in this toy example the
distribution are just a point masses. So
they are either like completely disjoint
or completely identical. But in general
real distribution have density.
So they have density so and they can be
partially overlap. So when there is
overlap with GS divergence the gradient
existence and can guide learning. But
again when the distribution do not
overlap the GS divergence becomes
constant. So it provides no use for
gradient. So now we have a clear
problem. K divergence blows up and JS
divergence becomes constant and in both
cases the loss is not sensitive to how
far theta is from zero. So it is not
give us a useful gradient and both of
them as we shown before are not
differentiable with respect to theta as
so here's a question how do we fix this
so given this a general idea is try to
use this le square g
instead of using cal divergence they try
to use a l2 loss this avoids the issue
of log going to infinity. So it fix the
problem we saw with KL
but it still does not really uh solve
the problem. The key issue is that the
learning signal still depends on the
discriminator. So as this uh plot shown
was shown this uh radar is a
discriminator.
So uh so if the discriminator becomes
very confident or behave poorly the
gradient can still be uninformative. So
it is does not really fix the vanishing
gradient problem. So you can see in this
picture it's the same uh situation as we
shown before. If this two distribution
become so far apart from each other this
discriminator becomes so confident and
so that this way the least square g
still depends on discriminator. So it
will still fail in this case.
So then in the given this we need a loss
that does not just avoid infinity but
also gives us a meaningful signal when
the distributions are far apart.
So here this leads to the versust
distance. So don't be intimidated by
this heavy attacks. uh you will see many
crazy bombers in the next few uh slides
and also including the crazy definitions
but don't get lost in them. Please focus
on the main idea like which is captured
in this figure. The main idea is very
simple. So the whole process is that you
can think of the generated distribution
as a pile of dirt and the real
distribution as a whole. here.
So the vasting distance matters how much
work it takes to move this dirt to fill
this hole, this real distribution hole.
So here mass simply means probability
and work means how much probability we
move multiply how far the distance is.
So this is exactly the optimal transport
problem. We want to move all this dirt
to fill this uh distribution hole. And
among all possible ways of moving it, we
choose the way with the minimum total
cost. However, solving this exactly is
computational very hard uh essentially
MP hard problem. We will see in the next
few slides how we can address this
issue.
Okay. Now let's make this idea more
concrete. Instead of thinking of dirt
and holes, we can represent this uh
process more explicitly. So as this
figure show at the bottom we have the
generated distribution PG and at the top
we have the real distribution PR. So the
matrix in the middle represent the
transport plan. each row corresponding
to a local in PG
and each column uh corresponding to a
location in PR.
So this matrix tells us how much
probability mass we move from each
distribution in PG to each distribution
to PR. Each entry corresponding to
moving some amount of mass from one
position to the another. So vesting
distance is the total cost of this plan
summing over all movements where each
cost is mass times distance.
And notice that the largest value are
often on or near the diagonal.
So this is because if the mass is
already in the right location, we don't
need to move it at all. So the cost is
zero. And even if it's not exactly
aligned, we prefer to move it nearby
locations to keep the cost small.
So now uh in the simple example we
discussed before where this the real
data is at zero and the generated data
is at theta. So let's try to solve this
by using sustained distance.
So what we do is just to move this mass
at theta to this mass at zero.
So the cost is exactly the distance
between them and multiply by the mass.
So as this figure show as theta moves
closer to zero the distance decreases
smoothly and form this V shift curve.
Okay and the key advantage is that this
loss is sensitive to distance. If theta
moves closer to zero the loss decreases
smoothly. So we get a useful gradient.
However, computing this exactly is very
hard. As we mentioned, we need to decide
how to move every small piece of mass.
Uh and there are too many possible ways.
So the problem is essentially empty
heart. So given this instead we use an
alternative formulation called the
cantoish rubistan duality to solve try
to solve this problem. So this tells us
that instead of explicitly move mass we
can compute the distance by finding a
function that maximize the difference
between its outputs on real and
generated data.
So this is where the this critic comes
in. Unlike a discriminator which tries
to classify real versus fake and outputs
a probability the critic outputs a real
value score. It is trained to assign
higher score to real data and lower
score to generated data. So instead of
telling us real or fake as the
discriminator do the critic trying to
tell us how far a sample is from the
real distribution and because of this
its output changes smoothly as the
generated sample move closer to real
data. So we get meaningful gradient
everywhere.
But this but this only work if we
control the slope of this function.
So the reason is that in this
formulation the function must be one lip
sheets meaning it cannot changing too
sharply. If we do not enforce this the
critic can become arbitrarily steep and
simp simply separate real and fake like
a classifier.
So we just uh just separating real and
fake with sharp jump. So in that case we
are just coming back to the same problem
as regular again that we mentioned
before where the function becomes flat
in most regions and gives no use for
gradients. So in the so uh in the
original wasusting gam paper this
constraint is enforced by weight
clipping uh where we directly restrict
the width to of the network to lie
within a fixed range. However, this can
make the function too restricted or
poorly behaved leading to unstable
training.
So instead, we enforce this constraint
by directly control the gradient. We
give a gradient penalty. We penalize the
gradient norm and keep it close to one.
So the function changing smoothly and
provide stable meaningful gradients.
With this constraint, the loss is smooth
and gives use for gradient even when the
distributions are far apart.
Okay, so this figure shows the
difference between a regular GAN
discriminator and a versing critic.
The red curve is a discriminator as we
shown before
which saturates and become flat near
this generated sample.
and the and the light blue uh line is a
vers critic here.
So you can see it's it stays smooth and
roughly linear. So it provides nonzero
gradient everywhere not like this
discriminator that pro provide no use
for gradient
and let's see how the processing gan
output look. The first row shows the
sample generated by the versesting G
here and the second row shows samples
from a standard again. The versing GAN
samples are more stable and structured
because the critic provides meaningful
gradients while the regular GAN samples
are noisy due to vanishing gradient. So
you can see
okay now let's move to the second main
problem of vanilla again which is mode
claps. So mode collapse happens when the
generator learns to produce only a small
part of the data distribution.
For example suppose the real data has
eight gshion mode. So each point
represent one gshion mode.
uh but you can see the generator learns
to map many different noisy inputs to
just one of the same
gausian mode. So you can see like during
the training it do not learn this eight
gion mode but just try to map to just
one of the gshian mode.
So, so even if this output looks
realistic, the model still fails to
capture the diversity of the data. And
so, most class the main issue is that it
limits the model uh generated samples
diversity. And one way to understand
this is through the training dynamics.
So, we can think of the discriminator as
defining a landscape over the data
space.
If several generated samples are closer
closer to each other,
then the gradient optics will push them
towards the same region that the
discriminator considers realistic.
And as a result, these samples clap to
the same point and keep moving together.
So even when the discriminator adapts
they still move together. So the
diversity is not recovered. So the
generator finds a shortcut. It
repeatedly produce a few outputs that
can fool discriminator instead of
learning the food distribution.
Okay. So mode claps is a a persistent
problem in GANs. it limit diversity and
will always produce repetitive autos. So
we need to pay attention in practice if
we work with GAN
and here are some solutions. One is mini
batch discrimination.
So you can see this is a regular process
of a standard GA. generator produce
images and produce images and send in
into discriminator to determine if it's
real or generated and also the image
from real data you can see from this two
line is also sent into the discriminator
to determine whether it's real or
generated.
However, the issue for the standard
again is that the determinator looks at
each image one at one at a time. So each
time it can only look at one image. So
it cannot tell whether the generator is
producing diverse uh samples or
repeatedly generating the same or a
small subset of images because it only
can see one image at a time.
So mini batch discrimination changes
this by allowing the discriminator to
look at multiple samples together
in a batch. So meaning a group of
samples proceed many of a group of
samples proceed at the same time. So
this way it can compare samples within
the batch and if like many generated
samples are very similar it can detect
this and penalize the generator.
And another approach uh to deal with
mode collapse is recessing gan which we
mentioned before because it loss depends
on the whole distribution collapsing to
one point still gives a large loss. So
the generator is pushed to spread its
output out instead of collapsing.
So to summarize, vanilla again has two
main problems as shown here. Vanishing
vanishing gradients and mode claps. And
besides the methods we discussed, there
are also many other techniques to
address these issues. Due to time, I
won't go into details here, but there
are good directions that you can follow.
Okay. Now let's move on to some
architectures on applications of GANs.
So GANs have roughly evolved through
five stages. They start with adding
control since vanilla GANs were hard to
control. Then came image to image
translation when we learn mappings
instead of generating from scratch.
After that uh models scale up with
attention and larger architectures to
capture global structure. This will uh
this was followed by stylebased model
that improve both quality and
controllability. And more recently we
seen uh we see transformer based and
hybrid models for better scalability and
flexibility.
Now let's look at some representative
and important architectures.
>> So first condition gans. Why do we need
g uh conditional gas? because sometimes
>> that's my that's my point. Go ahead.
>> Okay. So, because sometimes we do not
want a generative model to produce
images randomly. We want to control what
it generates. For example, I may want an
image of my friends, not someone else.
So the key idea is to add a condition to
the model so that the generation is
guided by what we want. Concretely, we
add a condition Y which can be a label
or some input to both the generator and
the discriminator.
So now the generator is not just trying
to produce something realistic. It can
also have to uh produce something that
matches the condition. At the same time
this discriminator is not just checking
whether the image look real or uh fake.
It also checks whether the image is
consistent with a given condition. So in
this way the model is no longer
generating arbitrarily. The condition
tells the generator what kind of image
to produce and the discriminator enforce
the realism and consistence with this uh
condition. So you can see one example of
the conditional GA output. Each row is
conditioned on one digit label. For
example, condition on zero, one uh up to
nine.
So after adding the condition, we can
see the model is no longer generating
random digits. It generate images that
match the given label while still show
variance within the digits.
Next, progressive GAN. One key issue we
mentioned earlier is that GANs are very
unstable especially when generating high
resolution images. So instead of
generating a large image directly
progressive GAN starts with a very small
image and gradually increase the
resolution.
Concretely, both the generator and the
discriminator are growing layer by
layers during the training. Starting
from a low resolution like 4x4 and
progressively adding new layers to each
higher resolution. At low resolution,
the model learn global structure. At
high resolution, it learns finer
details. So this is the example of the
high quality images generated by
progressive GAN. And now we come to
style GAN. So this diagram improves this
by changing how the latent code is used.
Instead of feeding the latent vector
directly into the generator
uh
into the generator it first pass through
a mapping network which transform it
into a new uh latent space. Then the
latent is injected into different layers
as scale. So you can see add two
different layers.
Concretely at each layer we first
normalize the feature map to remove its
original statistics and then rescale and
shift it to using parameter derived by
from the style vector. So we first
normalize to gather rid of the original
style and then we rescale to get get the
new rescaled im uh data. The key idea is
that different layers control different
level of the image and in addition
random noise is injected at each layer
which may affect small local details.
The model separates structured
information from randomness. The style
controls the structure and the noise
control fine varian variations. This
leads to much more interpretable latent
space where changing one direction can
corresponding to changing attribute like
age, hair color or pose. It's a bit like
a Photoshop layers like different layers
control different aspects of the image.
But here they generate the image
progressively not just stack the images.
So here now let's see how this figure is
generated by style GAN. On the left we
have source A.
Source A which is serve as a base image.
At the top we have source B which
provides add styles.
So this is a this is a simplified style
GA. So it have early middle layer and
later layers. We feed latent codes crazy
bounding to A and B into the same style
game model.
uh each input produce its own set of
styles which control different layers of
the generator. And to generate these
images, we start from the later latent
code of A and then replace the styles
with the those from B as specific layers
like either early layers, middle layers
or late layers. So for example in the
first block here
we replace the styles in the early
layers with those from B while keeping
the rest from A. Since early layers
control global structure the output
takes the pose and face shape from B. So
the changes are quite large.
And in the second block we only repeat
the styles in the middle layers.
So facial fe uh features change but the
overall structure stays like a and in
the last block we just replace the
styles in the final layers. So only fine
details like color and texture change.
So you can see that the overall face is
almost the same.
Now let's look at some GAN applications
for example image to image translation.
So image to image translation means
learning a mapping from one type of
image to another while preserve the
underlying structure keep the main
content the same. A natural start point
is this pix.
And then uh so the pix assume that we
have paired data and so we try to learn
a mapping between this paired data.
Here uh the the training combines a
reconstruction loss typically L1 which
preserves structure and then adversary
loss which improve realism. But in many
case we do not have pair data. So this
leads to cycle gang. Cycle gan learn how
learn two mappings one from domain x to
y one from y back to x.
So you can see from here
but this alone is not enough. The
mapping could still collapse or ignore
the input. So cycle introduce cycle
consistence.
If that means if we map from X to Y to X
hat
uh then we should recover the original
image still from this X hat to this X
and and this is enforced with a
reconstruction loss typically L1. So in
cycle uh cycle gan we have two signals
adversary loss control outputs looks
like the target domain and cycle loss
control output preserve original content
and now cycle was designed for two
domains. What if we have multiple
domains?
A straightforward way is to train
separate model for each domain pair and
uh during training we sample two domains
and apply cycle again. But this quickly
become inefficient and each model only
learn from two domains at a time. So to
solve this we use a star GAN. Star uses
a single generator and discriminator uh
to handle all domains. You can think of
it uh like combining matting pair wise
cycle cycle mappings into one model. So
it introduced a domain label as a
condition and so the generator takes an
input image and a target domain and
outputs the translated image.
So during training we randomly sample a
target domain at here
and the discriminator not only checks
real versus fake but also predict the
domain. So the output uh must match the
target. So real fake and also need to uh
match the domain. Styan also keeps cycle
consistent. So the model preserves the
mo main content while changing only the
attributes. And this is output of star.
So you can see the quality compared to
with between star and psychogen uh the
quantity for from star is much better
than the cycle. can see from here.
And in this image to image setting,
style G is also important because it
also allows us to control how the style
changes at different level. For example,
we can change global structure or only
fine appearance details. And finally, we
have this text to image. GAN text to
image translation means generating an
image from a given text describation. So
this is essentially a a specific
condition. Again, it's just that the
condition is test. So the generator
produced an image condition on the text
and the discriminator checks both
whether the image looks real and whether
it matches the description.
So you can see this is an example of the
output of tu image. So each time we give
this tax as condition and the model
generate the image given this condition.
Okay to wrap up GANs are essentially a
toggle. On one side we want the
generator to create masterpiece like
dinci and on the other hand we want the
discriminator to detect flows like
shallow combs. Thus progressive in GANs
in recent years has focused less on
changing architectures and more on
optimizing these dynamics and also in
the bigger picture this reflects a
generative dilemma. We cannot
simultaneously optimize speed quantity
and diversity. Gangs are still extremely
strong in speed and image quality but
their main limitation is stability and
diversity uh caused by the mode claps.
while different models which we learned
about in the last lecture uh offer
better diversity and stability but are
much more slower. So that's all for
today's lecture. Thank you all for
listening.
>> I have a question or two.
So we
still use guns since we have all these
other models that are performing better
because we saw there are some
disadvantages of of
>> So what was the key idea behind the
game?
>> The key idea behind the cam uh generate
images that are
look very real with
>> what was the key idea behind it? having
a discriminator.
>> Having a discriminator, right? The deaf
class, you can be stuck on anything.
So,
a generative model when you train a
generative model, you really have no
assurance that it's actually looking
like what you look like. You're just
maximizing likelihoods, right? So, uh uh
on the training data, it might just work
fine. But go outside the training data
and do you have any idea whether it's
generating something useful? I train a
generative model on lots of faces and I
give it a random input. Do you know that
it's going to produce a face or whether
it'll produce a table or a monkey?
You have no guarantee. Right? So that's
where this idea of having a
discriminator that's able to verify this
generating data not merely the training
instances comes in. And that's a very
powerful idea. So yes that idea consist
continues to remain valid because it's
fundamentally a different thing
>> and I have a question uh so just
empirical question but uh the
fundamental models that are generative
and like discriminative for generative
it would be like process and
discriminator would be like or something
like that so how do you make sure that
both of them have like the same capacity
or like equally powerful because you
don't
>> they don't I mean the discriminator has
to be needless capacity that the
generator has to because the genet has
to run a lot.
>> Thank you everybody. Thanks for coming
in. Thanks for voting.